Guide to the Stanford Historical Society Oral History Program Interviews SC0932
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
- Faculty and Staff Interviews, 2007-2016; Series 5
  - Street, Robert L., 2013 Jun 29
    Street was a Stanford faculty member from 1962-2004; he became an emeritus professor from 2005. Street focuses on numerical simulations related to geophysical fluid motions. His research considers the modeling of turbulence in fluid flows, which are often stratified, and includes numerical simulation of coastal upwelling, internal waves and sediment transport in coastal regions, flow in rivers, valley winds, and the planetary boundary layer.
    Street authored The Analysis and Solution of Partial Differential Equations and co-authored Elementary Fluid Mechanics. In addition, he is the author or co-author of one translation and about 230 archived proceedings and journal articles. Street received the American Society of Civil Engineers Huber Prize for distinguished research (1972), the American Society of Mechanical Engineers R.T. Knapp Award (1986; jointly with Jeffrey Koseff), and the ASCE Karl Emil Hilgard Hydraulic Prize (2002; jointly with Dr. Emily Zedler). He is the recipient of the 2005 Hunter Rouse Hydraulic Engineering Lecture Award of ASCE's EWRI and was elected a Distinguished Member of ASCE in 2009. He is a member of the Beverly Hills High School Hall of Fame (2005).
    He held a National Center for Atmospheric Research Senior Post-doctoral Fellowship in 1978 and a Faculty Fellowship in 2007; he was a Queen's Senior Post-doctoral Fellow in Marine Science [Australia] in 1985. He is a Fellow of the American Association for the Advancement of Science (1993) and a Member of the National Academy of Engineering (2004). He has served as civil and environmental engineering department chair, associate dean of engineering, and vice provost and dean and vice president in the university. At the University Corporation for Atmospheric Research, he has served as a Member of the UCAR Board of Trustees from 1983-1994 and as Chairman from 1987-1991. He is currently a member of the UCAR President's Advisory Committee on University Relations.
  - Strober, Myra H., 2014
    Myra Strober is Professor of Education, Emerita at the Stanford Graduate School of Education and Professor of Economics (by courtesy) at the Stanford Graduate School of Business. Her research and consulting focus on gender issues in the workplace, the economics of work and family, and multidisciplinarity in higher education. Her two-part interview begins with her early years in Brooklyn, New York, where her interest in economics formed. Strober recalls her undergraduate education at the School of Industrial and Labor Relations at Cornell University, her master’s program at Tufts University, and her doctoral studies at MIT, where she was one of only two women in her class. She relates how she eventually made her way to California, teaching as a lecturer at the University of California at Berkeley before taking an assistant professorship at the Stanford Graduate School of Business.
    Strober discusses her initial experiences teaching on the virtually all-male faculty at the Business School, her attempt to secure tenure there, and how she became a tenured faculty member at the School of Education. She recounts the events that led to the creation of the Center for Research on Women at the university and how she became its founding director. She discusses fundraising for the center and the lecture series that attracted overflowing crowds from the campus and neighboring areas. In addition, she discusses her service on the Committee on Recruitment and Retention of Women Faculty at Stanford and her experience as a sexual harassment advisor counselling female faculty members. She shares her perspectives on the challenges facing women in academia, such as a low percentage of women on the tenured faculty, salary disparity, and a lack of support.
    Strober also relates the story of how Stanford successfully competed to host and edit the preeminent women’s studies journal, Signs and its impact on the faculty and students involved. She discusses her research on occupational segregation, including her theory of how the relative attractiveness of occupations impacted work opportunities for women, and her research on childcare. Strober concludes with an assessment of some of the ways Stanford has changed over time.
  - Sunshine, Philip, 2014 Mar 31, Apr 21
    Philip Sunshine talks about his decision to pursue medicine, his education and his joining the Stanford medical school. He discusses the move of the medical school from San Francisco to Stanford and Robert Alway’s leadership. His also discusses the emergence of neonatal care as a discipline and the evolution of obstetrics-gynecology at the medical school. He shares his views on the state of neonatal care to date as well as on the anti-war student protests on campus.
  - Suppes, Patrick, 2010-2014
    Oral history interview conducted in May 2007. Topics include his activities with Dr. Fred Terman; Stanford's development into a major research university; his interests in logic, computers, learning theory and brain function; and the teaching of math.
    Patrick Suppes, Lucie Stern Professor of Philosophy Emeritus, was also director of Stanford's Institute for Mathematical Studies in the Social Sciences from 1959 to 1992.
    In his 2014 interview Patrick Suppes begins his interview with his recollections of Stanford and the philosophy department upon his arrival in 1950, including the influence of Frederick Terman on the direction of the university and across the departments. He continues with his interests in behavioral sciences and statistics and his responsibilities in the School of Humanities and Sciences. He discusses the developments in behavioral sciences and various events over the years, mentioning colleagues like Philip Rhinelander, John Goheen, Wallace Sterling and Paul Grice.
    Mathematics -- Study and teaching.; Mitchell, David W.; Terman, Frederick Emmons, 1900-1982; Suppes, Patrick
  - Thompson, George A., 2016-01-27
    George A. Thompson, Otto N. Miller Professor of Earth Sciences and Dean of the School of Earth Sciences, Emeritus, begins his interview describing his early life in Swissvale, Pennsylvania, his family, and early inclinations toward science. He continues on to his time as an undergraduate and master’s student at Penn State and MIT respectively, his work with the U.S. Geological Survey in West Texas, and his time spent in the navy before coming to Stanford to pursue his PhD under the mentorship of Professor Aaron Waters.
    Thompson also discusses his early teaching experiences at Stanford and the atmosphere of the newly formed Geophysics Department. Thompson goes on to describe going back to work with the U.S. Geological Survey in Nevada after graduating and later returning to Stanford as a professor. He further discusses his approach to teaching and his role in shaping the School of Earth Sciences as chair of the Department of Geophysics and Department of Geology. He notes his interactions with the administration after succeeding Allan Cox as dean of the School of Earth Sciences, appointing and evaluating junior faculty, and working with university donors such as Cecil Green.
    Thompson also discusses Earth Sciences’ connections with the oil industry and his memories of the Loma Prieta earthquake. He speaks of the consolidation of departments and changes in the School of Earth Sciences under new dean Gary Ernst. He then delves into his research in transition between the Sierra Nevada and the basin ranges, his time at Lamont Geological Observatory of Columbia University, fieldwork experiences in New Zealand, and the evolution of the disciplines of geology and geophysics. He describes his time on the USGS Advisory Panel and discusses issues of nuclear waste disposal and fracking. Thompson reflects on his involvement with geophysics and geology organizations, including the Geological Society of America and American Geophysical Union, and speaks about the notable awards he has received in his career. Thompson concludes the interview by discussing his family life, forestry work, and continued involvement at Stanford as an emeritus professor.
  - Traugott, Elizabeth C., 2012 Jun 5
    Elizabeth C. Traugott discussed her education and career in linguistics and English at Stanford, as well as her administrative career as the vice provost and dean of graduate studies. She discussed her experience working on the status of woman faculty at Stanford in terms of recruitment and promotion, the recruitment of ethnic minorities and women in graduate education, and the university’s growth to prominence since 1970s. She also compared her experience teaching at University of California, Berkeley and at Stanford.
    Elizabeth C. Traugott is Professor Emerita of Linguistics and English at Stanford University. Traugott has done research in historical syntax, semantics, and pragmatics, lexicalization, sociohistorical linguistics, and linguistics and literature. Her current research focuses on ways to bring the theories of construction grammar, grammaticalization and lexicalization together in a unified theory of constructional change; she is working on a book on constructionalization with Graeme Trousdale. She is also coediting the Oxford Handbook of the History of English with Terttu Nevalainen.
    Her publications include A History of English Syntax (1972), Linguistics for Students of Literature (1980; with Mary L. Pratt), On Conditionals (1986; co-edited with Alice ter Meulen, Judith Snitzer Reilly, and Charles A. Ferguson), Approaches to Grammaticalization (1991; co-edited with Bernd Heine, 2 volumes), Grammaticalization (1993, 2nd much revised ed. 2003; with Paul Hopper), Regularity in Semantic Change (2002; with Richard B. Dasher), Lexicalization and Language Change (2005; with Laurel J. Brinton), and Gradience, Gradualness and Grammaticalization (2010; co-edited with Graeme Trousdale).
    She has been an American Council of Learned Societies Fellow, a Guggenheim Fellow, a Fellow at the Center for Advanced Study in the Behavioral Sciences, and is a Fellow of the American Association for the Advancement of Science.
    Elizabeth C. Traugott received her PhD degree from the University of California at Berkeley in 1964.
  - Trimpi, Helen A. Pinkerton, 2016-03-17
    In this oral history, the writer Helen Pinkerton Trimpi recounts the path that led her to study English and poetry at Stanford University in the late 1940s and describes her experiences as a student of Ivor Winters and a lecturer in the Stanford Department of English. She reads her poem Autumn Drought (1976), which she wrote about Stanford and Winters.
    Trimpi begins with an account of her childhood in Butte, Montana and Mount Vernon, Washington. She recounts how Ray Cowell, her high school teacher and a Stanford alum, sparked her interest in journalism and encouraged her to apply to Stanford. Trimpi describes how her interest in English and creative writing, especially poetry, evolved at Stanford as she studied with the poets Ivor Winters and J. V. Cunningham. She describes being a student in Winters’ classes and speaks about the early days of the Stanford Creative Writing Program, which was founded by Wallace Stegner. Trimpi also describes student life at Stanford during the post-WWII period, including her experience writing columns for both the Stanford Daily and the Palo Alto Times while an undergraduate.
    Trimpi talks about meeting fellow Stanford student, Wesley Trimpi, whom she married in 1950. She recounts details of their travels in Europe, attending graduate school at Harvard, and their return to Stanford when Wesley joined the faculty of the Stanford English Department. Trimpi describes the culture of the department and talks about being a faculty wife and a lecturer in the English Department from 1962 to 1975. She discusses her opinion of curricular changes at Stanford and the women’s movement of the 1970s.
  - Turner, Paul Venable, 2012 Mar 5
    Paul V. Turner is the Phyllis Wattis Professor of Art, Emeritus, in the Department of Art & Art History at Stanford University since 1996. Professor Turner joined the Stanford faculty in 1972. He was chairman of the art department from 1991 to 1995, director of the Stanford Program in Paris, 1989-90, and chairman of the Hanna House Board of Governors, 1991-2006. Professor Turner also chaired the University Committee on Land & Building Development for several terms.
    Among the awards Professor Turner received are the Dinkelspiel Award for teaching from Stanford in 2001, and an Excellence in Education Award from the American Institute of Architects in 1993. Professor Turner also received grants from the N.E.H. Fellowships in 1977-78, 1985-86, the Graham Foundation in 1991, the Pew Foundation in 1983, and the Mellon Foundation in 1975.
    Professor Turner received his M.A. in 1963 and PhD in 1971 in fine art from Harvard University. He also received a master's degree in architecture in 1969 from Harvard Graduate School of Design.
    Paul V. Turner discusses early influences on his pursuit of architecture and how he became an architectural historian instead of a practicing architect, his research in Le Corbusier, his recollections of Lorenz Eitner, Al Elsen, John LaPlante and others, the evolution from the Department of Art and Architecture to the Department of Art and Art History, the challenges and accomplishments of the architecture program, his thoughts on Stanford's campus plan, his reflections on the Hanna House and Frank Lloyd Wright, and the challenges facing campus planning as the university continues to grow and expand physically, as well as academically.
  - Vincenti, Walter G., 2011
    Walter G. Vincenti discussed his career at Stanford University where he was one of the first professors hired for the Aeronautics and Astronautics Department and a cofounder of the Values, Technology, and Society program. He recalled his experience with Stephen Timoshenko, Stephen Kline, Robert McGinn, Nicholas Hoff, Edwin Good, and Nathan Rosenberg.
  - Voll, Peter R., 2011 Oct 24
    In this interview, Peter Voll recalled the origin and development of the Stanford Alumni Association’s Travel Study Program, 1968-1993. He touched upon the growth of the travel industry worldwide, and on the way the Stanford Alumni Association made use of the University’s growing connections with international leaders who had at one time or another been Stanford students. Individuals mentioned include Alice Coogan, Rixford K. Snyder, Tom Newell, Della van Heyst, Don Kennedy, and David Packard.
    In 1972 Peter (Stanford, 1965) joined the Stanford Alumni Association as a marketing consultant for the Stanford Alpine Chalet and soon after became the business/advertising manager of the first seven issues of Stanford magazine. In 1974 he took the reins of the Association’s fledgling Travel/Study Program, which he spent the next 18 years developing it into one of the premier alumni travel programs in the United States. Under Peter's leadership, the Travel/Study Program expanded from 3 programs in 1973 to more than sixty in 1992. He established Peter Voll Associates (PVA) in 1983 as an independent venture and in 1993 left Stanford to devote himself full time to PVA. A significant amount of his business was in the Middle East, and after 9.11. 2001, Peter merged his company with High Country Passage.
    For PVA and High Country Passage Peter organized, marketed, and managed educational tours for alumni associations, museum memberships, and special interest groups and corporations. Clients included Smithsonian Associates, American Museum of Natural History, National Parks and Conservation Association, National Audubon Society, National Geographic Expeditions, and National Trust for Historic Preservation; the Harvard, Princeton, Yale, Smith, Columbia, Stanford, MIT, Northwestern, Rice, University Chicago, UC-Berkeley, Cal Tech, UCLA, and USC alumni associations; and the Hoover Institution at Stanford University, Common Wealth Club of California, and the California Academy of Sciences.
    During his career Peter has designed and implemented more than 200 different educational tours to U.S. and worldwide destinations, by land, ship, train, riverboat, and private jet charter. He launched a number of travel industry firsts: tourist trips to the People’s Republic of China in 1978, and alumni tours to Burma (now Myanmar) in 1979, cruise tours to the Kingdom of Saudi Arabia in 1992 and land tours to the Kingdom of Saudi Arabia in 1997; in 1995 the first cruise ship voyages to the Arabian Gulf between Kuwait and Oman; in 1992 the first university alumni association charter of a Russian nuclear-powered icebreaker to reach the North Pole; the first private 727 expedition jet trip in 1991 to remote kingdoms in Africa. Peter has also served as a consultant in developing itineraries and educational tours for a number of tour companies, including Special Expeditions (now Lindblad Expeditions), Clipper Cruise Line, TCS Expeditions, and Zegrahm Expeditions. In addition, he has served as a consultant to the National Geographic Society and the Discovery Channel in the development of their travel programs.
    At a celebration of Peter Voll's career, shortly before his untimely death in 2012, Linda Burek of Palo Alto's Criterion Travel declared, "The program Peter developed (at Stanford) is the strongest in the business. It was ahead of its time. Now it's the mainstream. He set the benchmark. He brought everybody up." Steve Ridgeway, who looked upon Peter Voll as a mentor and with Voll helped establish Educational Travel Consultants, an annual conference of travel providers, said, "He really was a trailblazer."
  - Weiler, Hans N., 2016
    Hans N. Weiler, Professor of Education and Political Science Emeritus and the current Academic Secretary to the University, has had a distinguished career as an educator and administrator. In addition to his work at Stanford, Weiler served as the first president of Viadrina European University Frankfurt/Oder in Germany, and he also conceptualized the Hertie School of Governance in Berlin and served as its first leader.
    Weiler begins the interviews by clarifying that, although he began his career as a political scientist with a particular interest in Africa, he has had a foot in two camps at Stanford--the School of Education (later renamed the Graduate School of Education) and the Department of Political Science. He describes how he came to Stanford, citing the efforts of Professor of Education Paul Hanna, a visionary in international development education, and what Stanford was like in the mid-1960s. Weiler talks about Hanna’s role in the creation of the Stanford International Development Education Center (SIDEC) and the change in its leadership. He describes the interesting and significant work he did at SIDEC and the influential educators the center produced when its students went back to their home countries in Africa and Asia. He notes the connections that he developed in the field when he was on leave from Stanford for three years to direct the International Institute for Educational Planning, a UNESCO organization in Paris. He discusses his involvement with the Center for European Studies at Stanford and the challenge to area studies as a legitimate field.
    Weiler recounts other career milestones, including two very critical years in the 1980s as Associate Dean for Academic Affairs in the School of Education, when he placed graduate student funding in Education on a firm footing for the first time. Another milestone was his gradual transition out of African studies and into European studies amidst post-colonial reverberations in Africa and the reunification of Germany in 1989. Weiler recalls his work in remaking higher education in what had been East Germany, which eventually led to his early retirement from Stanford and becoming the first president of Viadrina. There, during two terms and in the face of various challenges, he tried to apply lessons regarding best practices in university education and administration he had learned at Stanford and in his research.
    Weiler goes on to talk about his retirement from Viadrina and taking on a unique task--the conceptualization and realization of the Hertie School of Governance, the first privately funded public policy institution in Germany. He recalls his decision, after nurturing the Hertie School to prominence, to come back to Stanford, and to the challenge/opportunity that he is still discharging, that of Stanford’s Academic Secretary. In addition to explaining his own role, Weiler discusses the origin and development of Stanford’s strong faculty governance system, the Faculty Senate, though he muses that it may be in need of redefinition at this point. He comments on the changes at Stanford since the 1960s, in particular the expansion of the university’s administration, the “gentrification” of the university, changing campus architecture, and the re-emergence of student activism.
    Having shared recollections of his career, Weiler talks about what it was like to grow up in Nazi Germany, describes his initial pursuit of Jesuit priesthood, and recounts his experience in the newly independent countries of Africa in the late 1950s that culminated in his devotion to African studies.
    Finally, Weiler compares Stanford and US higher education to European higher education, noting the ironic decline of liberal arts education in America at a time when it is gaining popularity in Europe and commenting on recent efforts in American postsecondary education.
  - Weissman, Irving L., 2014-04-02
    Irving “Irv” Weissman is a developmental biology professor at Stanford, where he is the Virginia & D.K. Ludwig Professor for Clinical Investigation in Cancer Research and the director of Stanford’s Institute for Stem Cell Biology and Regenerative Medicine. He was instrumental in the isolation and characterization of the first blood-forming stem cells, which give rise to all blood and immune cells in the body, and the cancer stem cells found in leukemia. In addition to his research activities, he founded three stem cell therapy companies, was involved in the formation of the California Institute for Regenerative Medicine (CIRM), and served on the National Academy of Science’s panel on human cloning in 2001. He earned his medical degree from Stanford University School of Medicine in 1965 and has held an academic position at Stanford since 1969.
    Weissman begins the interview by recounting his childhood in Great Falls, Montana and relating how, as a high school student, he was mentored by organ transplant pioneer, Ernst Eichwald. He describes his undergraduate studies at Montana State College and the research opportunities he had access to as a student in Stanford’s five-year medical school program.
    Weissman conveys his excitement with the immunology research done at Stanford in the 1960s, focusing on Henry Kaplan’s work with leukemia and the thymus, which led to Weissman’s own research focus. He recounts the experience of attending a meeting at the New York Academy of Sciences where James Gowans presented his findings on lymphocyte development, and the research he did in Gowans’s lab in Oxford to prove that lymphocytes migrate to the thymus where they develop into T-cells.